Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's daf is daf yud דף
י'. daf yud. We are a bissel ביסל bissel behind. We pick
up on amud bet עמוד ב' amud bet and we are dealing
with the mishna משנה mishna mentioned that both by a get גט
get for a woman and for a shtar shichrur שטר שחרור shtar
shichrur or a get shichrur גט שחרור get shichrur for a slave,
a writ of manumission, that they both say befanai nichtav uvefanai nechtam
בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. befanai nichtav uvefanai nechtam. And it said this
is one of the ways in which they're similar and then the
gemara גמרא gemara quoted a baraita ברייתא baraita that listed three or
four ways and actually that baraita ברייתא baraita is almost like a
foreshadowing of the next series of mishnayot משניות mishnayot because those cases
listed in the baraita ברייתא baraita are going to be dealt with
in the following mishnayot משניות. mishnayot. So let's just quickly review what
those are. You know, I guess I'll just, well, okay I feel
bad going back so quickly, so much, but let's just read from
the bottom of amud aleph עמוד א' amud aleph very quickly. Tanu
rabbanan תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, three lines from the bottom of amud
aleph עמוד א', amud aleph, bishlosha derachim shavu gittei nashim u'shichrurei avadim
בשלושה דרכים שוו גיטי נשים ושחרורי עבדים, bishlosha derachim shavu gittei nashim
u'shichrurei avadim, three ways they're the same and these are going to
be spelled out in also the coming mishnayot משניות. mishnayot. Shetzarich lomar
befanai nichtav uvefanai nechtam שצריך לומר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, shetzarich lomar
befanai nichtav uvefanai nechtam, you have to say befanai nichtav uvefanai nechtam
בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. befanai nichtav uvefanai nechtam. V'chol get sheyesh alav
ed Kuti pasul וכל גט שיש עליו עד כותי פסול, v'chol get
sheyesh alav ed Kuti pasul, any get גט, get, meaning any shtar
שטר, shtar, that has a Samaritan witness, ed Kuti עד כותי, ed
Kuti, is invalid, chutz migittei nashim u'shichrurei avadim חוץ מגיטי נשים ושחרורי
עבדים, chutz migittei nashim u'shichrurei avadim, except for a get גט get
for a woman and a writ of manumission for a slave. That's
an interesting leniency which we will see what that's about in a
minute or in coming mishnayot משניות. mishnayot. V'chol hashtarot ha'olim b'arkaot shel
akum וכל השטרות העולים בערכאות של עובדי כוכבים, v'chol hashtarot ha'olim b'arkaot
shel akum, all documents that come from non-Jewish courts, af al pi
shechotmeihem akum אף על פי שחותמיהם עובדי כוכבים, af al pi shechotmeihem
akum, even though there's non-Jewish witnesses that signed it, kesherim כשרים, kesherim,
are valid, which is amazing, a totally secular document. But the point
being is that as we'll see in the gemara גמרא, gemara, that
that's basically because it's just evidence. It's dinei mamonot דיני ממונות, dinei
mamonot, it's dina d'malchuta dina דינא דמלכותא דינא, dina d'malchuta dina, it's
evidence that the sale took place. So we can use those types
of documents the same way we do in our current life, if,
you know, we use the documents of sale that are processed through
the banks. We don't write up a, you know, like a halachic
shtar שטר shtar or something of that nature. Chutz migittei nashim u'shichrurei
avadim חוץ מגיטי נשים ושחרורי עבדים, chutz migittei nashim u'shichrurei avadim, with
the exception of a get גט get for women and a writ
of manumission for a slave, because those are not just evidence that
something happened, those are actually instruments to effect change of status and
it's about personal status. It's not just about dinei mamonot דיני ממונות.
dinei mamonot. So those of course have to be done classically according
to halacha הלכה halacha and are not good to use secular documents.
So those are three ways in which these things are similar. Now
the gemara גמרא gemara unpacks it. U'chedivrei Rabbi Meir b'arba'a וכדברי רבי
מאיר בארבעה, u'chedivrei Rabbi Meir b'arba'a, and according to the words of
Rabbi Meir רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir there's a fourth way. Omer ten
get ze l'ishti v'shtar shichrur ze l'avdi, ratza lachazor b'shneihem yachazor, divrei
Rabbi Meir אומר תן גט זה לאשתי ושטר שחרור זה לעבדי, רצה
לחזור בשניהם יחזור, דברי רבי מאיר. omer ten get ze l'ishti v'shtar
shichrur ze l'avdi, ratza lachazor b'shneihem yachazor, divrei Rabbi Meir. If a
person gives to a messenger a get גט get for his wife
or a shtar shichrur שטר שחרור shtar shichrur for a slave to
be delivered, then according to Rabbi Meir רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir he
can retract them before they've been delivered. Now why not? I mean
everybody should say you should be able to retract, it hasn't been
delivered yet. No, but the idea is according to the chachamim חכמים,
chachamim, you can't retract the one given to the slaves because they
say that that's definitely a zechut זכות, zechut, a merit, a benefit
for somebody to be free. And therefore as soon as you told
somebody deliver this to my slave, that person automatically becomes a representative
for the slave, zachin l'adam shelo befanav זכין לאדם שלא בפניו, zachin
l'adam shelo befanav, he can represent the slave's interests, he can assume
the slave would want to be free and become a shaliach שליח
shaliach for the slave, and his receiving of it even before he
delivered it to the slave is like he has been appointed by
the slave as a messenger and he automatically is, the slave is
automatically freed. So that's the normal, that's what the chachamim חכמים chachamim
say, that by a get גט get for a woman we can't
assume she wants to be divorced so she's not divorced until it
reaches her hand, but for the shtar שטר shtar of a slave
as soon as somebody receives it, he can act on behalf of
the slave.
But Rabbi Meir
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir disagrees...
right, so that's exactly, Rabbi Meir רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir disagrees and
Rabbi Meir רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's not necessarily in the
slave's best interest and we cannot assume that that's true and therefore
he's not freed until he actually receives the shtar שטר. shtar. Okay,
those are the ways in which these things are similar. Now the
gemara גמרא gemara unpacks it. Bishlama l'rabbanan minyana l'matuhei had'Rabbi Meir בשלמא
לרבנן מניינא למעוטי הדרבי מאיר, bishlama l'rabbanan minyana l'matuhei had'Rabbi Meir, it's
good for the rabbis, why do they say three ways? What do
they, when you say have a number, it means so you shouldn't
think it's more. It's interesting, you could just say it's a number
so that you remember them, but anyway the gemara גמרא gemara says
it's in order to exclude something else. So for the rabbis it's
a way of saying only three, not four, we don't include Rabbi
Meir's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir position, we don't think a get גט
get and a shtar shichrur שטר שחרור shtar shichrur are similar in
that way, a slave is freed as soon as the document is
given to the shaliach שליח. shaliach. So we're excluding Rabbi Meir's רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir position. Ela Rabbi Meir minyana l'matuhei mai אלא רבי
מאיר מניינא למעוטי מאי, ela Rabbi Meir minyana l'matuhei mai, what for
Rabbi Meir רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir when you say four, what are
you coming to exclude? What other case might you have wanted to
say would be the same? So the gemara גמרא gemara says l'matuhei
ha d'tanya למעוטי הא דתניא, l'matuhei ha d'tanya, to exclude what we
taught in a baraita ברייתא. baraita. Edim she'ein yodin lachtom עדים שאין
יודעין לחתום, edim she'ein yodin lachtom, let's say witnesses don't know how
to sign their own signatures, you know, they're illiterate. Okay? But these
are the only witnesses you can find. So what do you do?
Mekayemim lahem niyar chalak מקיימים להם נייר חלק, mekayemim lahem niyar chalak,
you tear a blank piece of paper, u'memalim et hakera'im d'yo וממלאים
את הקרעים דיו, u'memalim et hakera'im d'yo, and you fill the and
you fill the tears with ink, basically you do an etch-a-sketch. Not
an etch-a-sketch, what's it called? A stencil. You do a stencil, you
cut out the letters with a stencil and you have them fill
in the fill it in. Okay, so that's what you do if
they don't know how to sign their own names, which is not
much of a signature, I mean it's obviously... ink that they put
to paper that is the letters of their name, but it's not
distinctive in the sense of their handwriting because it's just filling in
the stencil. Anyways, that's what you do. Okay, that's that counts as
a signature. אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, *Amar
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel.
*Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*, במה דברים אמורים בגיטי נשים *Bameh devarim amurim
be'gittei nashim*. That can work for a גט Get, *get* for a
woman. אבל שחרורי עבדים Shichrurei Avadim. ושאר כל שטרות Shtarot, *Aval shichrurei
avadim u'she'ar kol shetarot*, but when it comes
to a writ of manumission or any other document, אם יודעים לקרוא
ולחתום חותמים ואם לאו אין חותמים *im yode'im likrot v'lachtom chotmim v'im
lav ein chotmim*. Okay, if they know how to read and to
sign they can do it and if not they can't. So it's
interesting. He's more lenient for a גט Get, *get* for a woman,
okay, than for which is the biggest thing in terms of personal
status than for any other document. So the obvious reason here is
is that it's a special leniency because of משום תקנת עגונות *mishum
takkanat agunos*. If this husband right if this guy wants to divorce
his wife and we're not going to find witnesses and he's never
going to be able to give her a גט Get *get*, so
you look at Rashi: בגיטי נשים *be'gittei nashim*. Rashi says I don't
even know where to tell you about 20 lines down in the
narrow lines, משום תקנת עגונות שמא יצא לפרש בים או מסוכן שרוצה
שלא תזקק ליבם *mishum takkanat agunos she'ma yetze l'farash bayam o mesukkan
she'rotzeh she'lo tizakak l'yavam*. They say he is about to go on
a long way trip. We would say maybe they're living apart and
they're effectively divorced but he hasn't given her a גט Get *get*
or maybe he's just not going to be living at home or
maybe he's about to die and there's going to be a יבום
*yibbum* situation. Sometimes you need that גט Get, *get* to be given.
So we'll make that leniency. But by everything else including שחרורי עבדים
*shichrurei avadim* we will not. אם יודעים לקרוא ולחתום חותמים ואם לאו
אין חותמים *im yode'im likrot v'lachtom chotmim v'im lav ein chotmim*. So
now anyway so that's what Rabbi Meir when he says four is
excluding. It's only similar to four here's a way in which they're
not similar. Okay and what's at least you know that a גט
Get *get* maybe you would have this leniency and you would not
have it by שחרורי עבדים *shichrurei avadim*. Okay so the Gemara says
קריאה מאן דכר שמיה *kriya man dachar shemei*? Wait a minute who
said read? We just were speaking about signing. What did he say
that שאר כל שטרות Shtarot *she'ar kol shetarot* if they know how
to read and sign you can do it? We've only been talking
about the signing problem not the reading problem. So the Gemara says
חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני Chasurei mechasra ve-hachi katani, *chisura mechsara v'hachi katani*.
It's missing some words and here's how you have to read it.
עדים שאין יודעים לקרוא קורין לפניהם וחותמים *edim she'ein yode'im likrot korin
lifneihem v'chotmin*. Even if the witnesses don't know how to read you're
dealing with really not only they don't know how to sign their
name they don't know how to read. Okay so what can you
do for them? You can actually read the שטר Shtar, *shetar* to
them and then provide them a stencil to fill it in. Okay
that's a lot that you're basically saying that that still counts as
testifying. ושאין יודעים לחתום מקרעים להם *v'she'ein yode'im lachtom mekarim lahem*. I'm
sorry I misread that excuse me excuse me I misread that. If
witnesses who
don't know how to read שאין יודעים לקרוא *she'ein yode'im likrot*. If
they don't know how to read
קורין לפניהם *korin lifneihem* you read it before them and then they
sign with their own signatures. And if they don't know how to
sign you also make the stencil for them. Okay so basically you
could wind up doing both for the witnesses. You can read it
to them and have them fill in their names within the stencil.
That's what you could do. But Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says no
that's a really special allowance we're only going to allow that by
גיטי נשים Gittei Nashim. *gittei nashim*. Okay by other types of things
we are not going to allow it. Okay so now one minute
okay right. Okay so that's what Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says. Now
by the way תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* asks an interesting question. If you
look at this little תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*, תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says קורין
לפניהם וחותמים *korin lifneihem v'chotmin*. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says the first wide
line: ולא הוי עד Ed מפי עד Ed, *v'lo havei ed mi'pi
ed*. תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* says one minute if you're reading me what's
in the document so I am not actually myself testifying to what's
in the document right? I only know what's in the document because
you're telling me it's in the document. So how can I sign
my name to it? Right? I'm not directly testifying to what's in
the document. So תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* says שאין צריך להעיד על עיקר
המעשה אלא Ella, שאומר שכך כתוב בשטר *she'ein tzarich l'ha'id al ikkar
hama'aseh ella she'omer she'kach katuv bash'tar*.
Okay right you can be reading you can be reading what's
in the שטר Shtar, *shetar* anyway right. Exactly. So he says
okay so he says wait a minute עד Ed מפי עד Ed
*ed mi'pi ed* שאין צריך להעיד על עיקר מעשה אלא Ela, שאומר
שכך כתוב בשטר *she'ein tzarich l'ha'id al ikkar ma'aseh ella she'omer she'kach
katuv bash'tar* בי שנים קמיה אפילו יחיד קמיה *bay shnayim kamei afilu
yachid kamei* etc. So this basically says right it's a little bit
funny because says but you're not עד ed מפי עד ed *ed
mi'pi ed* is you told me that a wedding took place and
I testify that a wedding took place. Okay but here I'm not
exactly testifying that the wedding took place I'm just testifying to what's
written in the document but still a little עד ed מפי עד
*ed mi'pi ed* you're telling me what's in the document and I
am signing my name to it. But it's a little bit different
because I mean תוספות *Tosafot* phrases it a little funny way. My
signatures I'm not testifying that the following words are written in the
document. My signature is saying I am testifying if like those words
in the document are the words that I am saying. So you're
telling me it's a little funny if you think about it. You're
like if I say let's say.
It's really that he saw the document written.
No עדות eidus, *edut* is well it depends what type of a
document it is. Right well no that's נכתב ונחתם עדות *nechtav v'nechtam
edut* but if it's like let's say it's the עדות *edut* that
says you know right that the husband
said to it's a funny but you know it depends on what
type of a document it is. If it's a שטר קנין Shtar
Kinyan, *shetar kinyan* like a גט Get. *get* then the it's not
then the what's testifying hasn't happened yet you know and then is
it that you're really testifying that it's the husband's will to divorce
his wife and that he. He commanded it, like you're saying, he
commanded it to be written in the גט. Get If it's another
type of document, let's say it's a document of bill of sale
and the sale took place and it's only testifying that the sale
actually took place, then it's testifying to past events. But anyway, it
is funny because normally we see that the words of the שטר,
Shtar. it's not so much that the עד is testifying that those
are the words written in the שטר, Shtar like I could read
that for myself that those are the words written in the שטר.
Shtar. It's more like the words that are written in the שטר
Shtar are the words of the עד, like the עד is actually
saying those words in the שטר. Shtar He is saying like what,
or a גט, Get right. Oh, for a גט, Get right, for
a גט Get? it's a little different. For a גט Get, it's
that the husband is, that's more the voice of the husband and
the עד is sort of testifying that the husband, like you know,
appointed that to be written or willed, was willed, expressed that desire.
Anyway, so right, so it's not exactly, that's the point, that depending
on what type of a שטר Shtar it is, if it's a
שטר ראיה, Shtar Rayah, it's like he's saying the words in the
document, and if it's a שטר Shtar. קנין, meaning the שטר shtar.
that effects a change in status, it's more that he's like validating
and creating it, but less that he's actually saying it. So it's
interesting either way what it means to be able to say those
words or know those words indirectly and not directly. All right, so
there are like two big חידושים Chidushim here. One is that something
counts as a signature when it's not your distinctive handwriting, and the
other thing is that it counts as being able to affix your
name to a document even if you don't directly know that those
are the words in the document. Okay, and both of those leniencies
we according, according to the תנא קמא, Tanakama, we allow those in
all שטרות, shtaros, which is pretty amazing. And according to רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, we allow it specifically by גיטי
נשים. Gittei Nashim But that's the case that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
was excluding. All right, so let's take a look now at the
next case. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to go and unpack
some of, like meaning,
meaning רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is excluding it, it means he's saying
that there is a difference.
Yeah, he's like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel Either
there's a difference, it's like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel. it's only by גט, Get, not by שטר שחרור, Shtar Shichrur,
or it's not clear to me, he could be like the תנא
קמא Tanakama and he could just be saying it's not unique to
גיטי נשים Gittei Nashim. and שחרורי עבדים. Either way, no opinion in
this case about reading it and stenciling it, no opinion says it's
a unique thing by a גט Get and a שטר שחרור. Shtar
Shichrur. It's either true by all שטרות Shtaros. or it's only true
by גט. get All right, so now we go on. Now the
גמרא Gemara looks at other cases. ותו ליכא? Vetu lika? Are there
no other cases in which עבד Eved and אישה Ishah is the
same? והאיכא? Veha'ika? האומר תנו גט זה לאשתי ושטר שחרור זה לעבדי
ומת לא יתנו אחר מיתה? ha'omer tenu get zeh l'ishti v'shtar shichrur
zeh l'avdi umes lo yitnu achar misah?
If somebody says, now notice it's in the plural, תנו, tenu, to
witness it. So basically give this גט get to my wife and
this, meaning write and deliver גט get to my wife, or write
and deliver because he's saying it in the plural, so presumably it
also has to be written, write and deliver this document of שחרור
Shichrur to my slave. ומת לא יתנו אחר מיתה, Umes lo yitnu
achar misah, and he dies,
they can't give it after he's dead because you know you can't
divorce your wife and you can't free your slave after you're dead.
It's only something you can do when you're alive. Now רש״י Rashi
says I don't get it, in the case of the slave didn't
we say that it takes effect immediately? So that's why תוספות emphasizes
that the language here is in the plural, תנו. tenu. If you
gave a גט get of שחרור Shichrur to somebody to deliver to
your slave and then that person dies, then the slave would be
freed the minute the שטר shtar got to the hand of the
other person. But here the guy, it isn't written yet. He's saying
to witnesses, when he says give, but he's saying it to, what?
זכי? Zachi? Okay, but that's implicit. If there's two people, if it's
in the plural, it means get a שטר שחרור Shtar Shichrur delivered
to my slave, means write it and deliver it. He's saying it
to two people. So in that case it's not written yet, nobody
can yet receive it for the slave and then he dies. So
obviously he's dead, you can no longer free the slave after the
master is dead. I mean the heirs could free the slave, but
you can't do it based on the command of the dead master.
And similarly about the husband.
Yeah, but if it was, let's say it already was there, like
there was a גט?
get That would be different.
Okay, but with the wife?
No, because, because you don't say זכי Zachi for the wife. Okay,
okay, now, לא יתנו אחר מיתה. lo yitnu achar misah. תנו מנה
לפלוני ומת יתנו אחר מיתה. Tenu maneh l'ploni umes yitnu achar misah.
Now let's say however the guy says, and let's say because also
when we're talking about אחר מיתה, achar misah, we could be imagining
we're talking about a deathbed case. He says give a hundred dollars
to so and so and then he dies, you do give it
after מיתה. misah. Why? Because that's an idea of מצוה לקיים דברי
המת. Mitzvah lekayem divrei hamet. Okay, there's an idea of doing something
when somebody commanded a deathbed wish, you satisfy it, you do it.
Okay, but that we sort of say when it comes to questions
about his distribution of his property. Issues about freeing the slave or
freeing the or divorcing the wife, well first of all divorcing the
wife obviously, even where you'd write a גט, get it wouldn't be
a כשר Kosher גט, get you know, for the wife
because she's now an אלמנה. Almonah. She's no longer married to the
guy, right. And similarly, you know, you can't write a גט get
for a slave now that he's owned by the heirs. You only
can write that with the, you know, will, it only constitutes a
legitimate writ if it's coming from the current husband or the current,
whatever, or the current owner. Okay, as opposed to money, money is
a question more of distribution of property, it's not a validity of
a שטר. shtar And that even though you could say well the
heirs now own the property, but nevertheless we sort of say well
the heirs now have a, like you know, there's a responsibility to
satisfy the wishes, the... wishes of the person. So that's why it's
יתנו לאחר מיתה. yitnu le'acher mitah. Okay? So there's another case in
which שטר שחרור shtar shikhrur and a גט get. are similar and
different from other types of things.
A slave's not considered property in the same sense as money
is considered
property.
Right, because a slave requires, it's not just like it requires to
free him. I guess if he said give my slave to ראובן,
Reuven, then maybe we would do that, then it would be total
sequence like money as property transfer of property, but free my slave
relates to personal status and it's seen as different and it requires
a special שטר שחרור shtar shikhrur and it's different than a transfer
of property. Now I said, I slightly I said it was about
מצוה לקיים דברי המת, mitzvah lekayem divrei hameit, רש"י Rashi says, we
look at רש"י, Rashi, תנו מנה לפלוני, Tenu Maneh lePloni, רש"י Rashi
says דברי שכיב מרע ככתובים וכמסורים דמי. Divrei Shchiv Merah Kechtuvim Uchimsorim
Dami. So רש"י Rashi says that it more is like actually, I
mean this is an interesting question in הלכה Halacha which I don't
want to get into right now, which is when is it an
issue about satisfying the person's deathbed wishes, which is an idea of
מצוה לקיים דברי המת, mitzvah lekayem divrei hameit, and when is it
an idea that if a person actually distributes his property on his
deathbed, it actually immediately like takes effect on his death as opposed
to being an obligation to satisfy his wishes, it actually automatically takes
effect, okay? And that's the principle of דברי שכיב מרע ככתובים וכמסורים
דמי. Divrei Shchiv Merah Kechtuvim Uchimsorim Dami. Right, there's a question of
why do you need you know why do you need the principle
of מצוה לקיים דברי המת, mitzvah lekayem divrei hameit, which is not
saying that it takes effect, it's just saying the heirs are supposed
to do it as opposed to as opposed to that's one idea
which the heirs have an obligation to do what he said as
opposed to דברי שכיב מרע
ככתובים
וכמסורים
דמי,
Divrei Shchiv Merah Kechtuvim Uchimsorim
Dami, which means that once he says something on his deathbed and
then he dies, it takes effect immediately when it comes to distribution
of property.
So there's a question then like the the document had been written
or...
no, well the question is if this if we're applying this principle,
then as soon as he dies, if I say give you know
I don't know give my car to Charlie or whatever, the guy
says give his car to Charlie and as soon as he dies,
Charlie automatically owns the car. Or do we say, no no, the
heirs now have an obligation to give the car to Charlie? Right,
so so... yeah but but in the in the situation where we're
talking about a document needing to be written, not something...
yes it does, and the גמרא Gemara is going to get to
the document in one second.
Anyway, so we're going to get right back to that. Anyway, so
when he says give a hundred dollars, it could fall in one
of those two categories, רש"י Rashi says it falls in the second
one, but either way when it's just about giving money we automatically
do that if a guy says it on his deathbed. But not
if it comes to divorcing his wife because anyway then she's an
אלמנה almanah or freeing his slave. So why don't we say that's
an area of comparison of those two? So the גמרא Gemara says
exactly what Jenna says. Let's take a look. כי קתני מילתא דליתא
בשטראות. Ki katani milta delaysa beshtaros. No, no, no. When we are
saying things that are similar between a גט get and a שטר
שחרור, shtar shikhrur, it's only those two, but not to other documents.
מילתא דאיתא בשטראות, Milta de'isa beshtaros, but something that would be not
unique to a גט get and a שטר שחרור, shtar shikhrur, it
would be true by all שטרות, shtaros לא קתני, lo katani, we
are not listing because that's not unique to a גט get and
a שטר שחרור, shtar shikhrur, it's something that's just part of them
being a שטר. shtar Now how is that true here? דשלח רבין
משמיה דרבי אבהו. Deshalach Ravin mishmei de'Rabbi Avahu. רב אבהו Rav Avahu
sent in the name of רב אבהו. Rav Avahu. הוי יודעי, Havei
yode'i, be aware, דשלח רבי אלעזר לגולה משום רבינו. deshalach Rabbi Elazar
lagolah mishum rabbeinu. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar sent to the exile in
the name of our master, which is I guess I guess רבי,
Rebbe, he sent the following teaching. I'm not sure who's anyway whoever
רבינו rabbeinu is. שכיב מרע, Shchiv merah, he sent the following thing.
שכיב מרע שאמר כתבו ותנו מנה לפלוני, Shchiv merah she'amar kitvu utnu
maneh lePloni, if he said write a document and give it for
a hundred dollars and give it to so-and-so, that would transfer a
hundred dollars to that person, but put it in a document and
give it to so-and-so. So in that case, לפלוני ומת lePloni umet
and he dies, אין כותבין ונותנין, ein kotvin venotnin, you don't write
it and give it. שמא לא גמר להקנותו אלא בשטר, Shema lo
gamar lehaknoto ela beshtar, because maybe he only wanted to transfer it
through a שטר shtar ואין שטר לאחר מיתה, ve'ein shtar le'achar mitah,
and a שטר shtar, doesn't work once the person is dead. A
שטר shtar requires, it's basically an expression you know of will of
the person who's giving it, and it only works if the person
who wrote the שטר shtar, is still alive. Okay, so therefore he
says this is not unique to גט get. and שטר שחרור, shtar
shikhrur, right? It basically is if anytime that somebody wants to transfer
something with a שטר, shtar you can't write a שטר shtar on
a person's behalf once they're dead. So if they want, whether they
wanted to divorce their wife, free their slave, or sell their house,
if they were doing it as a, do it through the writing
and delivery of a שטר, shtar, you could want to do it
or you could even go ahead and go through the motions after
the guy is dead, but it wouldn't take effect because a שטר
shtar, is meaningless if the owner if the if the principle of
the שטר shtar is not alive. can't do, as opposed to if
he's just distributing property without a שטר, shtar so then the property,
the transfer of ownership of the property could occur at the person's
death. All right? So if a person on his deathbed distributes property,
then on his death we say it almost becomes sort of inheritance
works. On the person's death, the people that he identified own those
properties that he was distributing. You don't need the person to be
alive for that to happen, that in a sense happens at his
death. But if it's to be delivered through a שטר, shtar the
שטר shtar can only be written and delivered while he is alive.
Yes. Oh, and the only thing about the concept, are we assuming
that the secretary says I'll give this guy $100, the secretary in
effect becomes a שליח shaliach for the receiver? I forgot one of
the things about שליח shaliach is to his benefit, so then it's
done. No, no, I mean, we'll have to see, I mean the
whole big thing in בבא בתרא Bava Batra סוף פרק sof perek
about שכיב מרע, shachiv mera, but it's more like it becomes a
type of a type of an assignment, it almost can become, I
mean there's a question conceptually how to see it, but it could
become almost like an assigning of heirs. When a person says I
want this person to get this and this person to get that,
it's sort of writing a will. It's a verbal will and then
it all takes effect on his death and then it gets distributed
the same way his property, the ownership of his property transfers at
his death to the heirs, it also transfers to the people that
he's identified. That's how it normally works. But that's saying that works
if all you're doing is distributing property. But if you're trying to
get a שטר shtar, written, you can't write a שטר shtar if
the principal is dead. So that's, yeah. So if he writes the
שטר shtar, and then the person dies, can he deliver that money
afterwards? No, I mean a שטר, shtar it's not just you can't
write it after the person is dead. It can't take effect after
the person is dead. Yeah, I'm sorry, I should be more precise.
Right. So right, even if a גט get is written, if the
guy is dead, she's already, I mean that's the most obvious case
because then she's already an אלמנה. almanah. But even in any other
case, even if it's about transferring ownership of the house, the שטר
shtar, only works if it's given when the principal is alive. All
right, yes. If a person on his deathbed says I want to
give so much money to so-and-so, does the person, does the giver
have to wait until the person dies and then he gives it?
Yes, yes, because if the person got better... exactly, it only takes
effect on his death, yes. Sorry, just a hypothetical. If he writes
a שטר, shtar gives it to a שליח shaliach and says free
my slave, then that would take effect... that would take effect immediately
because as soon as the שליח shaliach got it, it took effect.
Exactly. But if he had the שטר shtar written in his drawer
and he said give it to so-and-so after I die, then it
would be too late. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara continues the
following. All right. So that's not a point of similarity, or it
is a point of similarity, but it's not unique to a גט
get. and a שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: והא איכא לשמה? ve-ha ika lishma? הא בתר לשמה? ha
betar lishma? That's a requirement by גט get and by a שטר
שחרור shtar shichrur because we learn שטר שחרור shtar shichrur from גט.
get I mean we haven't spelled that out yet, but we learn
it from it. Okay. And that's something that's unique to those two
documents. Why wasn't that listed? So the גמרא Gemara says בשלמא לרבה
היינו מוליך ומביא. bishlama le-Rabbah haynu molich u-mevi. So according to רבה,
Rabbah, that's the point of saying that they both have to say
בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, bifnai nechtav u-vifnai nechtam, because one of the
things that that's about for רבה Rabbah
is לשמה, lishma, so it's implicit. אלא לרבא קשיא. ela le-Rava kashya.
But for רבא, Rava, why not list that as another point of
requirement of similarity, that they both require לשמה, lishma, because for him
that's not what בפני נכתב bifnai nechtav is about. So list that
as another point of comparison. So the גמרא Gemara says
ותו, ve-tu, and in addition, בין לרבה בין לרבא, bein le-Rabbah bein
le-Rava, according to either opinion, והא איכא מחובר. ve-ha ika mechubar. What
about the fact that neither a גט get nor שטר שחרור shtar
shichrur can be attached to the ground when it's being written? Okay,
because from both of them we learn like וכתב ונתן ve-katav ve-natan
or whatever, and we learn שטר שחרור shtar shichrur from גט אשה.
get isha. That you can't have anything that has to happen between
the writing and the giving. So that applies to both. So we
have all these other criteria that apply to both. So the גמרא
Gemara says no. כי תני פסולא דרבנן. ki tani pesula de-rabbanan. No.
Our list of three areas of comparison are rabbinic things that are
problems. דאורייתא לא קתני. de-oraita lo tani. Biblical requirements were not listed.
So now the גמרא Gemara says, really? So now we're going to
go back and look at the list of comparisons and see if
those are only rabbinic points and not biblical points. The גמרא Gemara
says one minute, והא ערכאות.
ve-ha arkaot. So remember, point number one was בפני נכתב. bifnai nechtav.
That's fine, that's rabbinic. But point number two was about having a
Samaritan signed,
so that could be rabbinic. Samaritans are Jewish and maybe there's some
problem that we have with them, but maybe that's only rabbinic. But
comparison number three was with the invalidity of a גט get and
a שטר שחרור shtar shichrur that's issued by a non-Jewish court. Well,
that would seem to me to be pretty biblical, right, that you
can't have a גט get issued by a non-Jewish court, which would
solve עגונה agunah problems if you could, right? But the גמרא Gemara
says so how could you say it's only rabbinic?
So the גמרא Gemara says והא ערכאות של עובדי כוכבים. ve-ha arkaot
shel ovdei kochavim. How about the non-Jewish courts? דפסולא דאורייתא הוא וקתני.
de-pesula de-oraita hu ve-katani. That's a biblical problem and that's listed in
the areas of comparison. So the גמרא Gemara says no.
באדי שיחרר רבי אלעזר.
be-edei shichrer
Rabbi Elazar. No, there's a way that that could only be...
That it's only a rabbinic problem.
How could it only be a rabbinic problem? That it's given in
front of kosher witnesses, and even though non-Jews signed it, it's delivered
in front
of kosher witnesses, and therefore according to Rabbi Eliezer for him the
witnesses that really matter are the witnesses that see it being delivered,
not the witnesses who sign. Now the funny thing is that might
be the act of delivery, but according to him it also has
to be written correctly, right? It's got to be written לשמה, lishma,
it's got to be written all those things. So you have to
imagine a scenario which is that somehow the document came out of
a non-Jewish court but was written לפי הלכה, l'phi halacha, which is
funny. I mean it has to be written by a Jew. So
maybe what it really means is you had a Jewish scribe write
it, but it got registered in the non-Jewish court, meaning when it
says it came out of the non-Jewish court it means that it
got signed and registered in the non-Jewish court but was written somehow
according to הלכה halacha and by a Jew. So that would be
the case. So it says we could imagine a case where it
was written properly, signed by non-Jews, and it's only a דרבנן derabbanan
problem according to Rabbi Eliezer. The גמרא Gemara says who says that
the witnesses that matter are the witnesses that it's been delivered in
front of? Okay? דאמר עדי מסירה כרתי. d'amar eidim mesira kirti. The
גמרא Gemara says one minute. והא מדקתני סיפא, v'ha midiktani seifa, the
end says רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon omer אף אלו כשרים, af
elu kshairim, even these even these documents are valid. We're going to
see that in a coming משנה. mishnah. Even when even when it's
signed by non-Jews, it's a valid גט. get It's pretty amazing. A
גט get? signed by non-Jews is a valid גט. get ואמר רב
זירא v'amar Rav Zeira and רב זירא Rav Zeira says ירד רבי
שמעון לשיטתו של רבי אליעזר דאמר עדי מסירה כרתי. yarad Rabbi Shimon
l'shitato shel Rabbi Eliezer d'amar eidim mesira kirti. So how could רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon say that signed by non-Jews is valid? So the
only way you could say it is if he's going like רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and says that it really matters the witnesses it
was delivered in front of, not the witnesses who signed it, okay?
So here what you have is the משנה mishnah later, I mean
we quoted a ברייתא braita but now we're relating to the משנה
mishnah later, says a גט get that comes from a non-Jewish court
with non-Jewish witnesses is invalid. Okay? And that's a way in which
גט get. and שטר שחרור shtar shichrur are the same. ורבי שמעון
v'Rabbi Shimon says it's valid. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who's saying
it's valid has to be following רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who says
you go by the witnesses, not the signed witnesses, but the witnesses
who saw it being delivered. Which implies that the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma who's saying it's invalid doesn't go by רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
and says it's invalid on a דאורייתא d'oraiteihu level because it's signed
by פסול pasul witnesses. מכלל דתנא קמא סבר לה, michlal d'Tanna Kamma
savar leh, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma holds that it's not valid,
it's biblically invalid because it's signed by פסול pasul witnesses. So the
גמרא Gemara says no. איכא בינייהו שמות מובהקין. ika beinaihu shemot muvhakin.
No, no, no, even the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma would only say
it's a rabbinic problem and the difference they both hold like רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, they both hold that it's biblically valid because it
is signed by because it goes by the witnesses who was given
in front. So what is the debate? The debate is maybe it's
even rabbinically valid. Now how could it be rabbinically valid? Because let's
say the witnesses have real good גוישער goisher names. It was signed
by Chris Christopherson, okay? So so in that case, okay, in that
case why should it be invalid rabbinically if it's valid biblically? Because
look, the reason you put the signatures on it was so that
you didn't have to go find the witnesses that actually saw it
delivered and you could rely on those signatures. So we're going to
have to rabbinically invalidate it because you're not allowed to rely on
those signatures because those signatures are non-Jews. That's only a rabbinic problem.
Biblically it was given in front of live witnesses, but rabbinically it's
invalid because we don't want you to rely on the signatures. But
comes along רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and says if those signatures are
obviously non-Jewish names, then I'm not even going to rabbinically invalidate it
because you're going to know you can't rely on it, okay? So
what the גמרא Gemara is saying is the debate is they could
both hold that it's biblically valid because it was given in front
of live kosher witnesses, okay, even though it has non-Jewish signatures on
it, and the debate is whether it's rabbinically invalid. And that's a
debate of are we going to rabbinically invalidate something that has obviously
non-Jewish names on it. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says yes, I'm
not going to allow any גט get with non-Jewish names. I don't
care if they're obvious or not obvious. That's too dangerous to let
that circulate and then you're going to rely on it. And רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no, that's fine. If you know and it's
obvious, I'm not afraid and you can use it. Okay? So biblically
they both agree it's valid because it was given in front of
kosher witnesses, okay, but the question is are we going to say
rabbinically it's invalid because you'll rely on the signatures and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon isn't afraid about that when the signatures are obviously non-Jewish.
Okay, so what the גמרא Gemara again you have to step back
and remind yourself what the גמרא Gemara is doing. The גמרא Gemara
is saying how come our list only consisted of three things of
comparison if there's these other comparisons as well, לשמה, lishma, מחובר, mechubar,
and so on. So the current argument is that the list is
only rabbinic invalidities. Now how could the list only be rabbinic invalidities
if one of the examples on the list is signed by non-Jews?
And the גמרא's Gemara answer is because we're assuming it goes by
עדי מסירה, eidim mesira, the witnesses that saw it delivered, so the
signatures of non-Jews is only a rabbinic problem and we're only and
therefore we're going once again. say that the list only consists of
rabbinic invalidities, not of biblical problems, okay? Because even such a גט
get is only a rabbinic problem cause we go by the witnesses
who were physically there. So now the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to say
one minute, והחזרה דאורייתא וקתני, Vahachazara de-Oraita ve-katni, one minute, the fourth
thing on the list was רבי מאיר'ס Rebbi Meir's point that once
the גט Get is delivered to the שליח, sheliach, you know, you're
still able to be חוזר, chozer, you're still the husband can still
retract, right, or the same when it's given to for it to
for delivery for the slave, the master can still retract. So the
ability to retract and to invalidate it is a biblical ability that
he can retract, right? So therefore we are talking about points of
biblical comparison, right? Biblically he can retract in that case. So you
can't say the list only consists of rabbinic ideas. אלא, fine, the
גמרא Gemara says forget that. We're not going to say that the
list is only rabbinic. Here's what we're going to say: כי קתני
מילתא דליתא בקידושין, מילתא דאיתא בקידושין לא קתני. Ki ktani milta d'leisa
b'kiddushin, milta d'isa b'kiddushin lo ktani. When we're talking about a list
about the things that are points of comparison, those are things that
are similar, that are true by גט Get and שטר שחרור shtar
shichrur and not true by קידושין. kiddushin. Okay, so let's go through
that. So the idea that for example you say that בפני נכתב
bifnei nichtav not required by a שטר קידושין, shtar kiddushin, there's no
עגונה agunah issue there, no reason to even if somebody is marrying
a woman, you can a man can marry a woman through a
שטר, shtar right? The שטר shtar, could say הרי את מקודשת לי.
harei at mekudeshes li. So let's say he's sending his שליח sheliach
to deliver the שטר shtar to a woman, okay, there would be
no בפני נכתב bifnei nichtav because we don't consider that an עגונה
agunah case, let them wait until they get together to get married
or something. So there's no בפני נכתב bifnei nichtav by שטר shtar,
for a woman. There's no we don't say עד כותי eid Kutsi
is כשר kasher by a שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin for a woman,
we'll see about the whole עד כותי eid Kutsi later. We don't
allow a שטר, shtar you know, coming out with non-Jewish signatures, you
know, that well that actually oh wait why would that be? That's
פסול, pasul, wait why would that not be a problem by a
woman? Hold on let me just check רש"י. Rashi. There goes. Oh,
that's interesting. So look at רש"י Rashi why the case of the
non-Jewish signatures would not be a problem by קידושין. kiddushin. So רש"י
Rashi is about five six lines before the lines get wide, רש"י
Rashi says like this, okay, וערכאות נמי ליתא בקידושין היכא דאיכא עדי
מסירה ישראל. v'erkaos nami leisa b'kiddushin heicha d'ika eidei mesira Yisrael. So
again we're assuming that there are kosher witnesses that see the שטר
being given over. So now what's the reason we invalidated it rabbinically
by the גט? Get לגט ושחרור הא דגזור דילמא אתי למסמך ומטרחינן
ליה לגיטא אחרינא. l'get u'shichrur ha d'gazru dilma asi l'mismach u'matrichinan lei
l'geta achrina. Because by גט Get we didn't want even though it
was given in front of kosher witnesses, we didn't want there to
be non-Jewish signatures because the woman would like rely on it, okay,
and you know you don't want to rely on non-Jewish signatures. אבל
בקידושין כיון דמדאורייתא מקודשת משום עדי מסירה אי אמרת אינה מקודשת שרית
אשת איש לעלמא. aval b'kiddushin kivan d'mid'oraita mekudeshes mishum eidei mesira i
amarta eina mekudeshes sharis eishes ish l'alma. So רש"י Rashi says like
the consequences, רש"י Rashi says like this, in both of those cases
there's a legitimate concern that we don't want you to rely on
non-kosher on non-kosher witnesses, okay? But the question is what's the consequence
of invalidating it? The consequence of like invalidating a גט Get would
be to say we don't consider you divorced. If you want to
get divorced you need to write another גט. Get So there's like,
I mean, there's a downside in terms of the woman that she's
not divorced but there's no like concern of an elite halakhic violation
to invalidate it. Whereas by a שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin if we
said we invalidate the שטר, then she'd go ahead and marry another
man, right, and that'll be like a huge cost and a huge
consequence. So that's like how רש"י Rashi explains the difference. All right,
תוספות I think has another explanation but we won't worry about that.
So basically what it is saying is that those points of comparison
are things that are true by שטר שחרור shtar shichrur and by
a גט Get and not true by קידושין kiddushin as opposed to
לשמה lishmah and מחובר. mechubar. לשמה lishmah and מחובר mechubar are both
actually requirements by a שטר קידושין. shtar kiddushin. It can't be written
on something מחובר. mechubar. It has to be written לשמה, lishmah, okay,
so those are. So I think that this is probably getting way
confusing for people, I'm sorry. I always am lacking in things to
erase, but okay here we go anyway. Let's go through the things,
okay? We have בפני נכתב, bifnei nichtav, here are the things that
are written: בפני נכתב, bifnei nichtav, עד כותי, eid Kutsi, okay, ערכאות
erkaos which are basically you know עדי עכו"ם, adai akum, okay, non-Jewish
witnesses. Those are the three. And then רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir has
חזרה, chazara, you know being able to retract after it was or
not being able to retract, okay? So the גמרא Gemara says it
could say all these three are rabbinic. This and this is obviously
rabbinic. How would this be Rabbinic if it's non-Jewish signatures? So it
says עדי מסירה *adei mesira*. So that's why we're only listing things,
because the question is why not include, here is the... most question,
why not include לשמה Lishmah? *lishma* and מחובר *mechubar*? Those are also
points of comparison. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* first says no, these
are דאורייתא *de'oraita*, you know, and this these are Rabbinic. If this
was עדי מסירה *adei mesira*, then even non-Jewish witnesses are Rabbinic. But
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says one minute, the ability to retract is
also דאורייתא *de'oraita*, right? The ability to retract. That's not a Rabbinic
point. So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*... so that can't be the reason
why we have this list and we didn't include those two. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is now saying the difference is is that
whether these things are unique to this and these are unique and
would not be true by קידושין kiddushin. *kiddushin*. לשמה Lishmah *lishma* and
מחובר *mechubar* not only do you require it by גט Get *get*
and שטר שחרור shtar shichrur: *shtar shichrur*, you also require it by
שטר קידושין *shtar kiddushin*. Okay, because we learn out שטר קידושין *shtar
kiddushin* from גט Get *get* and we require the same requirements. These
things only apply by גט Get *get* and שטר שחרור Shtar Shichrur?
*shtar shichrur*, do not apply by קידושין *kiddushin*. This doesn't apply by
קידושין *kiddushin* because there's no עגונה *aguna*. This doesn't apply by קידושין
*kiddushin* what we'll see later what that's about. Okay, this doesn't apply
by קידושין *kiddushin* because... oh, the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is going to
ask that this should also apply by קידושין *kiddushin*. If I say
to a שליח *shaliach*, go give this, you know, ring to to
this woman and make her my wife, I obviously can retract before
she gets it, right? So that's going to be... that's going to
be the question the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*'s going to ask. But this,
why does a שטר *shtar*... a שטר קידושין *shtar kiddushin* with non-Jewish
witnesses even if there are עדי מסירה *adei mesira*, why is that
פסול pasul דרבנן D'rabbinic *pasul de'rabbanan*? So basically רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* says
the cost would be too high to invalidate this דרבנן *de'rabbanan* by
a שטר קידושין *shtar kiddushin*. So none of these things are problems
by קידושין *kiddushin* whereas these are. So that's this list is only
saying things that are by גט get? *get* and שטר שחרור Shtar
Shichrur *shtar shichrur* and not by קידושין *kiddushin*. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to focus on the חזרה *chazara* issue.
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this: one minute. והחזרה גופה איתא בקידושין *Ve'hachazara gufa ita be'kiddushin*. What
about חזרה *chazara*? That exists by קידושין *kiddushin*. If I give a
שליח *shaliach* a ring to give to to a woman to marry
her or a שטר *shtar*, I can retract before the woman gets
the ring. Okay, she's... it's not necessarily true she wants to be
married to me, so I can retract. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says no, בשליחות בעל כרחה *Bishlichut ba'al karchah*. No, the point is
is that is that שחרור *shichrur* and a גט get? *get* can
be done against the will of the woman and of the slave,
right? It's בעל כרחה *ba'al karchah*. And it could be done against
their will. A woman doesn't get married unless she wants to. But
גט get *get* and a שטר שחרור Shtar Shichrur *shtar shichrur* can
be done against the will. And therefore, the idea... there is no
הוה אמינא *hava amina*, this is how תוספות *Tosafot* explains it. There
is no question that I can retract if I give a שליח
*shaliach* I say here, here's a ring, go marry that woman to
me. There's no question I can retract like everything is still a
big question whether she's going to accept it or not. It's all
based on her will. So of course there's no question that, oh
my god, as soon as I gave him the ring she's married.
What do you mean? There's a whole other side that has to
agree to it. So the ability to retract is obvious there. But
when I'm divorcing my wife or if I'm freeing my slave, it's
all a one-sided act, right? They get no say in it. So
in that case you might have thought that I could actually... that
once it's done it's done, I can't be חוזר chozer *chozer*. So
there you have to be מחדש *mechadesh* that I that I can
still be חוזר *chozer* in that case even though it's one-sided. Okay,
so what the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*'s saying is you know what, you're
right. In all cases, גט get. *get*, שטר שחרור Shtar Shichrur, *shtar
shichrur* and קידושין *kiddushin*, I can be חוזר *chozer* before the other
side gets it. Okay? However, it's not a חידוש *chiddush* by קידושין
*kiddushin*. By קידושין *kiddushin* there's a whole other side that gets to
decide. So of course it's not done just because I gave it
to the שליח *shaliach*. The חידוש *chiddush* is by גט get? *get*
and by and שטר... and שטר שחרור Shtar Shichrur *shtar shichrur*, there
I might have thought it was done as soon as I gave
it to the שליח *shaliach* and the answer is it's not. Okay,
even there I can be חוזר *chozer*. Okay? דבשליחות בעל כרחה דבגירושין
איתא בקידושין ליתא *De'bishlichut ba'al karchah de'be'geirushin ita be'kiddushin leita*. All right,
so we are now done with that very complicated גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
yes. Even שטר שחרור Shtar Shichrur *shtar shichrur* you can't retract once
you gave it to the... according to רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir*, you
can retract both because it's not even a שטר שחרור Shtar Shichrur
*shtar shichrur* is not necessarily he says in the best interest. According
to the חכמים *Chachamim* you can't. Now we're dealing with רבי מאיר
*Rebbi Meir*. רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir* says for both you can retract
because it's not necessarily in the best interest. So תוספות *Tosafot* says
yeah, here there's a חידוש *chiddush* that you can retract by a
גט get, *get* and שטר שחרור Shtar Shichrur, *shtar shichrur* because it's
all unilateral. So I might have thought you're not able to and
even there we say you are because the other side still has
to receive it. They don't have to agree to it, but they
still have to receive it. So therefore this is within רבי מאיר
*Rebbi Meir* who says it's... who says you can retract, okay? By
קידושין *kiddushin* it's much more obvious, okay? Anyway, all right, so I'll
have to end this with a joke because that was such hard
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So about the ability about קידושין *kiddushin* having another
side. So a guy goes to a... somebody says I have a
great שידוך *shidduch* for your for your daughter. Who? says the Prince
of Wales. says the Prince of Wales, are you kidding? He's a
גוי *goy*! says yeah, I know, but the ייחוס *yichus* and his
looks and he's got you know, he's so חשוב *chashuv* or whatever.
Guy says you're nuts! Anyway, day after day, week after week, month
after month he's האקן א טשייניק *hakn a tshaynik*. Anyway... Finally after
like a year he says okay fine I'm מסכים. So the guy
says great now I just have to talk to the other side!
All right so anyway. All right so that's why you can be
חוזר by קידושין. All right so anyway. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Next משנה. Mishnah. כל גט שיש עליו עד כותי פסול.
Kol get sheyesh alav ed kuti pasul. Now after that complicated thing
we're now going to actually look at each case individually and it's
going to be a little bit easier. כל גט שיש עליו עד
כותי פסול. Kol get sheyesh alav ed kuti pasul. Any get that
has a Samaritan witness is invalid, that we said. And that's similar
to—excuse me—חוץ, chutz, excuse me, anything meaning any שטר is invalid. Here's
the interesting leniency by גט get and שטר שחרור: חוץ מגיטי נשים
ושחרורי עבדים, Chutz migittei nashim veshichrurei avadim, except interestingly by the more
weighty documents, a get for a woman and a divorce writ of
manumission, there a Samaritan witness is okay. מעשה שהביאו לפני רבן גמליאל
לכפר אתוני או עתני Maaseh sheheviu lifnei Rabban Gamliel l'Chfar Atunai o
Otnai גט אשה, get ishah, they brought a get of a woman
to him in this village. והיו עדיו עדי כותים Vehayu adav adei
Kutim and the witnesses were Samaritan witnesses. והכשיר Vehichshir and he said
it's valid. Now that's interesting because until now we said עד כותי
ed kuti in the singular, which sounded like you needed at least
one, you know, Jew and one Samaritan. This sounds like even if
both of them are Samaritans. We'll see that in the גמרא. Gemara
But here we have this very interesting leniency and we have to
figure out what that's about. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara So the גמרא Gemara says מאני מתניתין? Mani matnitin? Who's our
משנה Mishnah going like that we're lenient by a Samaritan? לא תנא
קמא ולא רבי אלעזר ולא רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Lo Tanna Kamma
velo Rabbi Elazar velo Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. Not the Tanna Kamma,
not Rabbi Elazar, not Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. Why, what does that
mean? דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, three interesting opinions
about the status of Samaritans. מצת כותי, Matzat kuti, a מצה matzah
baked by a Samaritan. מותרת, Muteret, it's permissible, it's not considered חמץ.
chametz. We think that they're very careful about the מצוה mitzvah of
חמץ chametz and they—you don't have to be afraid of that that—they,
you know, if they're going to eat it on פסח Pesach
so it's not חמץ. chametz. ומותרת, Umuteret, excuse me,
שאדם יוצא בה ידי חובתו בפסח. she'adam yotzei bah yedei chovato b'Pesach.
Not only are we saying it's not חמץ, chametz, we're saying that
they were שומר shomer it לשם מצת מצוה leshem matzat mitzvah
and you can eat it for—you
can be יוצא yotzei for your מצוה mitzvah of מצה matzah on
פסח Pesach night. Okay, actually it was משתמרת. mishtameret. Okay, if you
look at רש"י, Rashi like three lines into the גמרא, Gemara, I
mean רש"י says
יוצא בה ידי חובתו בפסח משום
חובת לילה ראשון שהוא חייב לאכול
מצה משתמרת.
yotzei bah yedei chovato
b'Pesach mishum
chovat laila rishon shehu chayav leechol
matzah mishtameret. It's not only is it not חמץ, chametz, it's even
considered to have been watched for the right purpose כדכתיב וערב תאכלו
מצות. Kedichtiv uvaerev tochelu matzot. ואפילו ידינו בו שלא החמיצה לא נפיק,
Vaafilu yadinan bei shelo hechmitzah lo nafik, even if we know for
a fact it isn't חמץ chametz it wouldn't—that wouldn't be enough to
be יוצא yotzei your מצוה mitzvah of מצה, matzah, אלא אם כן
עבד לה שימור לשם חובת מצה. Ela im ken avad lah shimur
leshem chovat matzah. You have to watch it for the purpose of
being יוצא yotzei the מצוה mitzvah of מצה. matzah. Now that sounds
like one of those classic תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al peh types
of ideas that you would not expect the Samaritans to necessarily agree
with. And nevertheless the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma here is saying you
assume that they are so careful by the laws of חמץ chametz
and מצה matzah that even that—that not only can you eat their
מצה matzah and assume it's not חמץ, chametz, but you can even
assume that it satisfied all the criteria of מצה, matzah, okay, and
it was watched for the purpose of מצה. matzah. Okay, now by
the way the important thing here is as a debate elsewhere, right,
whether the Samaritans are actually Jewish or not Jewish. When they converted
at the end of the בית ראשון Bayit Rishon period, right, the
whole story there in the נביא Navi which is that, you know,
is that—you know, the Samaritans were sort of brought into the ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael by—you know, and then the—and then they were like—they
just did their old pagan practices. And then lions came and attacked
them and then they, you know—and then they were told oh yes,
the God of this land you have to follow his laws and
so on. Anyway, so then the question is okay, well then did
they—was that—did they convert? You know, what exactly is their status? So
that's debated in the גמרא. Gemara Everybody here assumes that they are
Jewish. The question is they might be Jewish but they certainly had
their own form of practice. It wasn't exactly Judaism. Okay, you know,
they had their own ספר תורה Sefer Torah and whatever that had—that
had significant differences. So that's the question here. They are Jewish, but
how much do we assume that they—that they follow the מצוות mitzvot
that we can rely on them? So the first opinion said you
can rely on them, not only is it not חמץ chametz but
you can even be יוצא yotzei your מצוה mitzvah of מצה. matzah.
That's the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. Okay, so now it says like
this: רבי אליעזר אוסר לפי שאין בקיאין בדקדוקי מצוות. Rabbi Eliezer oser
lefi she'ein beki'in bedikdukei mitzvot. Rabbi Eliezer says no, they're not careful
with the details and you know, devil's in the details or God's
in the details, הלכה's halacha in the details. Anyway, if they're not
careful with the tiny details so it might not be who knows,
like it's not only can you not be יוצא yotzei the מצוה
mitzvah of מצה, matzah, you have to be concerned it might actually
be חמץ. chametz. Okay, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר כל מצוה שהחזיקו
בה כותים הרבה מדקדקים בה יותר מישראל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer
kol mitzvah shehecheshiku bah Kutim harbeh medakdekim bah yoter mi-Yisrael. No, any
מצוה mitzvah that they have seized onto, they're even more meticulous than
the Jews, okay, than naturally born Jews. So anyway, presumably and מצה's
matzah one of them. Now exactly how do you know, you know,
and for the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, does the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma say for all מצוות mitzvot they're careful about? Like what exactly
is the debate between—רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel sounds
like you have to know that this is a מצוה mitzvah that
they've embraced. Okay, but it's not exactly clear like— For the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma whether you would know what standard you would know
about whether this is the מצוה, Mitzvah, maybe תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
feels all מצות. Mitzvos. Or תוספות basically has a whole discussion, maybe
for תנא קמא Tanna Kamma it's all biblical מצות Mitzvos they're careful
about and for רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, you know, you have to
know it's a מצוה Mitzvah they embraced, but if they embrace it
they're super careful even at the דרבנן level. So it's not exactly
clear, right, how, you know, which category of, you know, for רבן
גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, which מצות Mitzvos they are careful about, but certainly
מצות Matzos is one of them. Anyway, that's the debate. So now
the גמרא says like this. Okay. מני. Manni. Now who is our
משנה Mishna that allows for a Samaritan witness going back, but only
for a גט get and a שטר שחרור? אי תנא קמא, Ee
Tanna Kamma, if it's the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, אפילו שאר שטרות
נמי, Afilu Sha'ar Shtaros Nammi, right? So then for the תנא קמא,
Tanna Kamma, he doesn't make distinctions. He feels like you can trust
כותים Cutim for everything, so then it shouldn't be a difference what
type of document. אי רבי אליעזר, Ee Rabbi Eliezer, if it's רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, he doesn't, he seems to not trust them for
anything. He says that they're not careful, so אפילו שטר שחרור נמי
לא, Afilu Shtar Shichrur Nammi Lo, right? תנא קמא Tanna Kamma seems
to totally accept them and they're good and you can rely on
them period. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you can never rely on
them. The only one who seems to say sometimes yes, sometimes no
is רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. Okay? ואי רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל, Ve'ee Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, so then it depends:
is it something they've embraced or not something they've embraced? אי דאחזיק,
Ee D'achzik, if they've embraced this, אפילו שאר שטרות נמי, Afilu Sha'ar
Shtaros Nammi, you should trust them for other documents. אי דלא אחזיק,
Ee D'la Achzik, if they haven't embraced it, אפילו גט אשה נמי
לא, Afilu Get Isha Nammi Lo, even not, even גט אשה Get
Isha not. So now of course רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel is the most obvious choice to go because with him
you can distinguish between the categories. So the most obvious thing to
do is to say the next thing the גמרא suggests. וכי תימא
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל היא, Ve'chee Teima Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel Hee,
let's say our משנה Mishna is רבן שמעון Shimon. בן גמליאל. ודאחזיק
בהא, Ved'achzik Be'ha, but he says, right, תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says
you can always trust him. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you can
never trust him. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל says sometimes yes, sometimes no,
so he's the perfect one to say גט get? and שטר שחרור
yes, other things no. וכי תימא רבן שמעון בן גמליאל היא ודאחזיק
בהא, Ve'chee Teima Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel Hee Ved'achzik Be'ha, they're careful
about גט get and שטר שחרור and therefore you can trust them
in that area. ולא אחזיק בהא, V'lo Achzik Be'ha, but not by
other שטרות. So that works. Okay, that seems to be a perfect
answer. גמרא says no. אי הכי, Ee Hachi, says the גמרא, if
that's true, מאי אריא חד, Mai Irya Chad, then why can you
only trust one witness? אפילו תרי נמי, Afilu Trei Nammi, you should
also be able to trust two. Right, if it's basically saying here's
an area you can trust כותים Cutim in by גט get and
שטר שחרור, so then it should be you can trust two of
them. אלא למה אמר רבי אליעזר, Ella Lama Amar Rabbi Eliezer, why
does רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say לא הכשירו בו אלא עד אחד
כותי, Lo Hechshiru Bo Ella Eid Echad Cuti, right? It says עד
כותי, Eid Cuti, only one כותי Cuti witness as long as one,
but one is a Jew בלבד. Bilvad. So there's no good way
to explain this. If they really are believed in the area of
גט get and שטר שחרור and not other places, you should accept
both. Why is it that you accept only one? Now I do
want to parenthetically say, what does this mean that they've embraced this
area? Like it's one thing to say they've embraced שבת, Shabbos, they've
embraced מצה. Matzah. What does it mean to embrace signing documents, right?
So what does it mean? Now you could say by a גט
get, and a שטר שחרור there is a question: do they believe
that you have to sign it לשמה? Right? We have the לשמה
requirement. So there is like a ritual aspect that they have to
embrace. But what does it mean that they've embraced גט get and
שטר שחרור but not other documents? So what do they think about
other documents? They don't understand? What does it mean embrace? Is it
a הלכה? Halacha? You're saying פלוני Ploni sold the plot of land,
you know, sold his house to ראובן, Reuven, sold his house land
to שמעון. Oh well, they haven't embraced that מצוה. Mitzvah. What מצוה
Mitzvah you talking about? So it sounds like we're talking about like
whether they feel that you have to be like honest and truthful
when you sign documents. So what is it? The מצוה Mitzvah of
עדות שקר? Eidut Sheker? It's a question of honesty, right? It's a
little funny. So then what the גמרא is really saying is, oh,
when it comes to גט get. and שטר שחרור, that's about personal
status. They would never lie about that. That they're going to be
serious about. They won't put their names to a document that's about
personal status that's actually not true. But if it's just about somebody
selling somebody else a house, yeah, they'll put their names even if
it's not true, they'll lie. I mean it's a funny type of
a split. It's about lying as opposed to, like, embracing a ritual
requirement. Yes. It is funny, but it's interesting if you think about,
like, in Israel, the secular community, where, like, they're not going to,
you know, necessarily care about the religious requirements in many things, but,
like, they want their גיטין Gittin and they want, right? Like, that's
true. So for like a religious requirement to say like they care
about גט get and they don't care about שבת Shabbos or whatever,
I could understand, but they care about גט get but they don't
care about signing truthfully to bills of sale. It's like, that's, you
know what I'm saying, like, that's not a ritual thing, you know,
it's a little, it's a little strange. Okay, now the other thing
to note, by the way, that תוספות and I should point out
is that another גמרא says and even if they're careful in מצות
Mitzvos who says that they're careful about your מצות? Mitzvos? Meaning the
גמרא discusses the whole לפני עיוור Lifnei Iver issue. If they don't
believe in the לפני עיוור Lifnei Iver problem, maybe if you go
to their house you can eat their מצות, Matzos, but how do
you know they can bake מצות Matzos for you? I won't eat
this sort of like the king's like taster of the food or
whatever. I’m not going to eat this מצה matzah until you eat
it first or something. So that’s like another aspect, right, which is
sort of which is funny because on the one hand okay logically
it makes sense, but it also raising that problem creates that tremendous
amount of distrust between the communities. Right? It’s like one thing to
say like I you know you’re not so מקפיד makpid on you
know on this area I don’t know if I can eat the
food or whatever that’s maybe it’s not great but it’s an objective
assessment. But to say even if you are מקפיד makpid I don’t
know if that you know you’re going to you’re caring about you
know that that means that what you’re feeding me is כשר. kosher.
Again, that might be true, could be that they really didn’t care,
you know, and there was sort of antagonism between the communities. So
it does raise that other issue. Anyway, so the גמרא here says
even if you were to say you can trust them by גיטים
Gittin and not by other saying not by other documents, why would
we only allow one? We should then allow two. So the גמרא
says ואולם רבי אליעזר. V’ulam Rabbi Eliezer. Fine, it’s רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, we don’t have to say they’re careful. We could say that
they’re generally רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says they’re not careful as a
rule about documents at all including גיטים. Gittin. So then why do
we trust one witness by a גט? get Okay? וכגון דחתים ישראל
לבסוף. U’kegon d’chasim Yisrael l’vasof. But the story is is that you
have a ישראל Yisrael signing below the כותי. Kusi. That’s why we
allow only one, one כותי Kusi and one ישראל Yisrael signature underneath.
And then we can say the following: דאי לאו דכותי חבר הוה,
D’i lav d’Kusi chaver hava, if this כותי Kusi was not a
trustworthy guy, okay, לא הוי מחתים ליה מקמיה, Lo havei machtim lei
mikamei, the ישראל Yisrael would not have allowed the כותי Kusi to
sign before him or another way of saying that the ישראל Yisrael
wouldn’t have signed under the כותי’s Kusi name. I’m not going to
affix my signature after that כותי. Kusi. He’s not a guy you
can rely on. So implicitly by the fact that I put my
signature below his is I basically have testified to the fact, validated
the fact that this was a trustworthy כותי. Kusi. Now תוספות raises
the obvious problem here. If that’s true, really the whole document relies
on one person’s signature. Right? You understand? The only reason you know
you can trust the signature before me is because I’m testifying that
it’s valid. So it’s all relying on my testimony. But תוספות says
okay but anyway biblically you could trust the כותי Kusi signature. We
said before these are only rabbinic concerns about their trustworthiness here in
signing a document. So that’s why we allow one signature because my
signature came afterwards. So the גמרא says one minute, אי הכי Ei
hachi says the גמרא, if that’s true, אפילו שאר שטרות נמי. Afilu
shear shtaros nami. So let that be good even by a normal
document that my signature comes after the כותי. Kusi. Why only by
a גט? get אלא, why don’t we allow it by another document?
אמרינן Amrinan we say, רווחא שבק למאן דקשיש מיניה. Ravcha shavik l’man
d’kashish minei. Maybe I was asked to sign a document and I
said you know what I’m going to put my signature on the
second line because I’ll let somebody more important than me sign before,
okay? And therefore the fact that my signature appears second doesn’t mean
I validate, implicitly acknowledge the previous signature. Maybe I left that line
blank and then you went and you got somebody else to sign
it you know you know ten minutes you know in a different
room or you know down the street. So I didn’t know that
the כותי Kusi was signing before me. I just left a blank
line before it, okay? So הכא נמי Hacha nami that’s why you
can’t trust it by another document, הכא נמי Hacha nami by a
גט get, too, רווחא שבק למאן דקשיש מיניה. Ravcha shavik l’man d’kashish
minei. Maybe I left a blank line and I signed my signature
on the second line and I let somebody more important sign first
and you told me maybe you even told me you were going
to get somebody more important, okay? But then what happened was that
person wasn’t available so you got a כותי. Kusi. So the fact
that the כותי Kusi signed before me doesn’t prove that I acknowledged
the validity of that signature. So if that’s true by other documents
it’s true by a גט. get So how then do you explain
why yes and why by a גט? get So אמר רב פפא
זאת אומרת Amar Rav Pappa zos omeres this tells you עדי הגט
Eidei ha’get and here’s the answer because when it comes to signing
a גט, get עדי הגט אין חותמין זה בלא זה. Eidei ha’get
ein chasmin zeh belo zeh. Everybody has to be in the room
at the same time and everybody has to sign in everybody’s presence.
So this heightened requirement by a גט get, that doesn’t apply by
other documents that everybody has to be in the room and sign
in everybody’s presence, so because we made that higher demand it also
though means that if there’s any question about the witness it’s better
because the witnesses afterwards were present when they signed the גט get
and they’re implicitly validating the previous witness, okay? So מאי טעמא Mai
ta’ama now what’s the reason we have this higher requirement by a
גט? get. אמר רב אשי גזירה משום כולכם Amar Rav Ashi gezeira
mishum kulchem because we’re afraid that the guy will say by a
גט get I can say I want all of you in this
room to be my witnesses. And in that case the גט get
is פסול passul unless everybody signs. Now that’s not true by other
documents. Any other document it’s just two people, two men makes עדות,
makes it a valid document, end of story. But because a גט
get is so much the sort of will of the husband sort
of like you know you know embodied in the גט, get, that’s
sort of how the גט is seen, my desire to divorce my
wife expressed and embodied in the גט. And I can say that
this will not be a valid גט unless everybody here signs. Now
that's true, what's going to happen if I say that and then
you all scatter and you say, okay, you know what, but you
know, but you know, Jonathan, I'm going to go to you and
you're going to sign, and I'm going to tell you don't worry,
I'm going to go around and get everybody else to sign, and
then I get like two or three of these people but I
don't get all of them, and then I deliver the גט to
my wife? Now, she's going to think she's divorced, there's two kosher
signatures on it, but הלכה halachically she's not because I demanded that
everybody do it. So once I've made the demand that everybody do
it, you all need to refuse to sign unless everybody's in the
room, because if you agree to sign without everybody being in the
room, the גט's going to wind up looking kosher and it's going
to be פסול passul because it's not going to have everybody's signature
on it. Is that clear? Right? Yes? Why when I made... if
I made the demand that you all need to sign, then you
should refuse to sign without everybody being present. Exactly, more than two
witnesses signing, and if I made the demand, it would be פסול
if you didn't have all those witnesses. So once I've made that
demand, you should all... what? Why does that stipulation exist? Well, because
we're going to see, because the idea is that a גט somehow,
because as I was saying before, is an expression of the will
of the husband, there's an understanding that somehow the husband can shape,
you know, what makes it a valid גט, meaning I can make
more demands, not fewer, obviously. And I can say that this will
not be a valid גט unless everybody here signs. Well, we'll see
that later, but that that is true. But once that's true, you
have to refuse to sign without everybody being present, or I'm going
to make have something look like a kosher גט which isn't. And
once that's true, when I do say כולכם, kulchem, you all have
to be present, we're just going to make a general rule that
anytime signatures sign on a גט they all have to be present.
And once that's true, if there's a כותי Kuti signature on a
גט, we can say that it's valid because obviously everybody was present,
so therefore they're implicitly acknowledging the validity of that signature. But how
do you know the number of witnesses that the husband said had
to be there? You wouldn't. But that's why once we make this
requirement we... I mean, or maybe to bring witnesses to say... You
mean how could he challenge the גט afterwards? Okay, but maybe again,
maybe he could bring witnesses to testify to the fact that when
he initially made that demand. Yeah. So let's just finish up, I
know we're a little over, but let's just at the end we'll
go quickly here. גופא, Gufa,
so let's go back and see what he said before. אמר רב
אלעזר לא הכשירו בו אלא עד אחד כותי בלבד. Amar Rav Elazar
lo hechshiru bo ela ed echad Kuti bilvad. מאי קא משמע לן?
Mai ka mashma lan? תנינא. Tanina. What do you
have to say only one? That's in the משנה. Mishna. כל גט
שיש עליו עד כותי פסול. Kol get she-yesh alav ed Kuti passul.
It says עד אחד echad except for גיטי נשים. So it's clear
even עד אחד, echad, it's clear we're only talking about עד אחד.
echad. No, אי מהמתניתין, Ei me-ha-matnitin, if it was our משנה, Mishna,
הוה אמינא אפילו תרי נמי. Hava amina afilu terei nami. You could
even have two witnesses that are כותים Kutim to be kosher by
a גט. ובהא דתני חד, U-ve-ha de-tani chad, why did it say
one? משום דבשטרא אפילו חד נמי לא. Mishum de-vishtara afilu chad nami
lo. It's telling you that by other שטרות even one כותי Kuti
witness is no good. But maybe I would think by a גט
two would be valid. קא משמע לן, Ka mashma lan, so רב
אלעזר Rav Elazar says no, even by a גט we only allowed
one כותי Kuti for the reason we said before because you need
the other witness signature to validate it. גמרא says תרי לא? Terei
lo? Are you telling me two are not kosher? והקתני, Ve-ha-katani, the
end of the case says מעשה והביאו לפני רבן גמליאל לכפר אותנאי
גט אשה והיו עידיו עדי כותים והכשיר. Maaseh ve-heviu lifnei Rabban Gamliel
li-Kfar Otnai get ishah ve-hayu eidav edei Kutim ve-hechshir. There were witnesses,
were כותי Kuti witnesses, and he validated it. So you see for
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel two witnesses are good, כותי Kuti witnesses. אמר
אביי Amar Abaye תני עידו. Tani eido. So אביי Abaye takes out
the י. yud. It says its witness was, okay, he takes it
out. רבא אמר Rava amar לעולם תרי. Le-olam terei. No, no, no.
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel actually keep it in. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
allows two כותי Kuti witnesses. רבן גמליאל מיפלג פליג. Rabban Gamliel miflag
palig. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel argues, he's even more lenient. חסורי מחסרא
והכי קתני, it's missing some words and here's how you have to
read it. רבן גמליאל מכשיר בשנים. Rabban Gamliel machshir bi-shnayim. רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel says even two כותי Kuti witnesses are kosher, maybe because
he said like before, maybe like he feels like you can generally
trust כותים Kutim like that other opinion. Okay. ומעשה נמי שהביאו לפני
רבן גמליאל לכפר אותנאי גט אשה והיו עידיו עדי כותים והכשיר. U-maaseh
nami she-heviu lifnei Rabban Gamliel li-Kfar Otnai get ishah ve-hayu eidav edei
Kutim ve-hechshir. And he said it was kosher. So what do you
have? You have the general assumption that you don't trust כותים Kutim
for signing, but by a גט it's okay because of the demand
that everybody be present for later signatures after the כותי Kuti implicitly
validate the כותי Kuti signatures. That's why it's good, but only one.
And רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel maybe is of the opinion that in
general you can trust כותים Kutim in their signatures of גיטין. Gittin.
And therefore רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says even if both of them
are כותי Kuti signatures, maybe he would even allow something that wasn't
a גט, maybe in general he trusts כותים Kutim and therefore for
him even if both of them sign you are fine. Okay. Or
maybe again, maybe it's something that the כותים Kutim are good in
terms of גיטין, Gittin, not other things, but either way in this
case he trusts כותים Kutim and therefore for him even both of
them would be okay.